A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Deputy Director, Office Files of Gordon L. Berlin FA605
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Deputy Director, Office Files of Gordon L. Berlin
1979-1988
Rockefeller Archive Center
Berlin, Gordon
Ford Foundation
FA605
2.85 Cubic Feet 8 Hollinger boxes
The Urban Poverty (UP) Program was established as a subdivision of the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) in October 1981, taking over programs formerly administered by the divisions of National Affairs and Education and Public Policy. It administered programs benefiting the poor and inner-city residents in areas that included community development, employment and training, welfare, teen pregnancy, poverty, crime, and precollege education. In 1988, UP became a separate division, and in 1996, was merged into the Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS). Gordon L. Berlin served as a Program Officer in the Urban Poverty Program from 1982 to 1987 and as its Deputy Director from 1987 until he left the Foundation in June 1988. He oversaw programs in employment, training, labor supply, welfare, and related educational issues. He also served on task forces, such as the Foundation's Task Force on Growth, Development and Employment (1984-1987) and the National Service Task Force (1984-1986). The Office Files of Gordon L. Berlin primarily consists of Program Files containing reports, data, research, notes, memoranda, and correspondence relating to such issues as national service, summer youth employment, workfare/welfare reform, remedial education and workplace literacy, preschool education and daycare, and school drop-out rates of at-risk youth. There are also some conference materials, subject and correspondence files, and a few speeches and writings relating to these and similar issues.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Biographical / Historical
The work of what became the Urban Poverty Program began when the Public Affairs Program was formally established in 1952. One of the goals of the new program was to work toward greater equality of opportunity for minority groups. In 1965, Public Affairs was succeeded by the National Affairs Division, created to focus on deep-rooted problems facing American society. Program areas under the National Affairs Division included Social Development and Urban and Metropolitan Development. In 1981, a reorganization of the Foundation replaced National Affairs with the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP).
The Urban Poverty Program was established in October 1981 as a subdivision of USIAP, taking over programs formerly administered by the divisions of National Affairs and Education and Public Policy. It administered programs benefiting the poor and inner-city residents in areas that included community development, employment and training, welfare, teen pregnancy, poverty, crime, and precollege education. It also assumed oversight of the programs in Population and of new programs to combat infant and child mortality. The Urban Poverty Program became a program area within a newly organized Program Division in 1988 and was merged into the Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) in 1996.
Biographical / Historical
Gordon L. Berlin received a B.A. from University of Charleston (1974) and an M.A. from George Washington University in Science, Technology and Public Policy (1976). Prior to joining the Ford Foundation in 1982, he worked for the Office of Research and Development in the U.S. Department of Labor. Mr. Berlin served as a program officer in the Urban Poverty Program from 1982 to 1987 and as its Deputy Director until June 1988 when he left the Foundation. He oversaw programs in employment, training, labor supply, welfare, and related educational issues.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 4 series.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Gordon L. Berlin document his work as a Program Officer (1982-1987) and as Deputy Director of the Urban Poverty Program (1987-1988). Throughout his time with the Foundation, his work focused on labor and unemployment issues. In addition, Mr. Berlin served on task forces, such as the Foundation's Task Force on Growth, Development and Employment (1984-1987) and the National Service Task Force (1984-1986). He also continued to research and write about the difficulties of the school-to-work transition for economically and educationally disadvantaged young adults (1985).
Series I. Conferences, 1982-1987
This small series consists of four Conference files. They hold information retained by Mr. Berlin about conferences he organized or attended, including reports on events, agenda, lists of participants, and related correspondence. The conferences include the Aspen Institute and Public Agenda Foundation conference at the Wye Plantation, MD (1982), the Computer Education Conference in Bangor, MA (1983), the National Service Meeting in New York, NY (1983), and the Russell Sage Foundation Poverty Meeting in New York, NY (1987).
Series II. Program Files, 1979-1988
The largest series in the collection, the Program Files consist of reports, data, research, notes, memoranda, and correspondence on a variety of subjects related to Foundation program activity. Arranged alphabetically by subject, the files document Mr. Berlin's work relating to labor, welfare, and education. Multiple files on the same subject have been arranged chronologically.
Several files pertain to Mr. Berlin's previous interest in welfare reform, the retraining of industrial workers for employment in other fields, and preparing impoverished youth for employment (e.g., see folders titled "Basic Skills, Education and Employment," 1979-1985.) There are also files documenting his long working relationship with economist Robert Taggart that include information about efforts made by Mr. Berlin and the Foundation to support the awarding of a MacArthur Fellowship award to Dr. Taggart (1982-1987).
Series III. Speeches and Writing, 1983-1985
This series of three files contains Mr. Berlin's statement to a joint Congressional and Senate Field Hearing on the subject of youth employment (1983), a draft article titled "Employment and Income Generation, Plant Closings and Worker Ownership" with editorial comments by Susan Berresford (1984), and a speech titled "The Foundation's Youth Work, Service and Learning Strategy: A Site Visit Overview" given to the Trustees before a tour of three youth programs (1985).
Series IV. Subject and Correspondence Files, 1982-1987
This series contains chronologically arranged correspondence files and alphabetically arranged subject files. Topics of subject files include the appointment of consultants (1982) and affirmative action (1985).
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
- Conferences, 1982-1987; I
  Scope and Contents
  This small series consists of four Conference files. They hold information retained by Mr. Berlin about conferences he organized or attended, including reports on events, agenda, lists of participants, and related correspondence. The conferences include the Aspen Institute and Public Agenda Foundation conference at the Wye Plantation, MD (1982), the Computer Education Conference in Bangor, MA (1983), the National Service Meeting in New York, NY (1983), and the Russell Sage Foundation Poverty Meeting in New York, NY (1987).
  - Aspen Institute and The Public Agenda Foundation -- Conference on Jobs in the 1980s and 1990s, Wye Plantation, MD, 1982 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Computer Education Conference, Bangor, MA: Agenda, Correspondence, Participant List, 1982 September 1-1983 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National Service Meeting, Ford Foundation, New York, NY -- Memoranda, Invitations, Agenda, Participant Lists, Background, 1983 November 18-23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Russell Sage Foundation Poverty Meeting, New York, NY -- Memoranda, Background, 1987 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Program Files, 1979-1988; II
  The largest series in the collection, the Program Files consist of reports, data, research, notes, memoranda, and correspondence on a variety of subjects related to Foundation program activity. The files document Mr. Berlin's work relating to labor, welfare, and education.
  Several files pertain to Mr. Berlin's previous interest in welfare reform, the retraining of industrial workers for employment in other fields, and preparing impoverished youth for employment (e.g., see folders titled "Basic Skills, Education and Employment," 1979-1985.) There are also files documenting his long working relationship with economist Robert Taggart that include information about efforts made by Mr. Berlin and the Foundation to support the awarding of a MacArthur Fellowship award to Dr. Taggart (1982-1987).
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by subject. Multiple files on the same subject have been arranged chronologically.
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- Memoranda, Data and Analysis from NLS Findings (1 of 3), 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- Memoranda, Data and Analysis from NLS Findings (2 of 3), 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- Memoranda, Data and Analysis from NLS Findings (3 of 3), 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- Memoranda and Analyses Re: 1979 NLS Findings (1 of 3), 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- Memoranda and Analyses Re: 1979 NLS Findings (2 of 3), 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- Memoranda and Analyses Re: 1979 NLS Findings (3 of 3), 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- Data, Memoranda, Notes, Papers on Youth Education and Employment, 1982 March 24-1985 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- "Education Attainment, Academic Ability, and the Employability and Earnings of Young Persons" (report Re: JTPA Youth Programs), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- "Youth Employment Problems, Causes, and Cures" (report), 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- "Educational Attainment, Academic Ability, and the Employment and Earnings of Young Persons" (report), 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- AFQT (Armed Forces Qualification Test) -- Memoranda and Data (1 of 2), 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- AFTQ (Armed Forces Qualification Test) -- Data, Analysis, Notes (2 of 2), 1986 February 19 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- Correspondence Re: Feedback for "Education, Equity and Economic Excellence" (report by Gordon Berlin and Joanne Duhl), 1984 February 1-1985 March 5 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Basic Skills, Education and Employment -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Interview, Notes Re: Youth Unemployment and Illiteracy, 1984 June 29-1987 October 27 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Budget for Youth Employment -- Memoranda, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Business Development -- Memoranda, Article, 1986 September 11-1987 January 28 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Displaced Workers and Industrial Policy -- Correspondence, Report (separated), 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Education -- Math Program -- Correspondence, Papers, Discussion Participants List, 1986 August (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Education -- Rural Education Task Force Memoranda Re: Meeting, 1986 October 23 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ford Foundation Project on Social Welfare Policy -- Memoranda, Proposals, Speeches, Notes, Reports (separated), 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Grameen Bank Employment and Income Generation Task Force -- Memoranda, Discussion Papers, Background, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Job Training -- Role of Community-Based Organizations in Youth Job Training -- Memoranda, Symposium Summary, Notes, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Job Training -- Status Report on Youth/Private Sector Initiatives, 1982 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Job Training -- "Training, Learning, and Computers" (report by Gordon Berlin), 1982 August 8 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Job Training -- Youth Employment Working Group Meetings -- Agenda, Reports, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Job Training -- Public/Private Ventures -- School/Business Collaborations Interim Report, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Literacy, Remedial Education and Employment/Workplace Literacy -- Status Report on Program Explorations Related to Literacy Problems, Memoranda, 1983 March (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Literacy, Remedial Education and Employment/Workplace Literacy -- Memorandum Evaluating "The Role of Remedial Education in Improving School Achievement" (report), 1983 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Literacy, Remedial Education and Employment/Workplace Literacy -- Andrew Sum Analysis of NAEP Literacy Assessment Findings, 1986 October (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Literacy, Remedial Education and Employment/Workplace Literacy -- Growth, Development and Employment (GDE) Task Force Meeting, Salzburg Seminar, 1986 December-1987 April (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Literacy, Remedial Education and Employment/Workplace Literacy -- Karl Haigler Correspondence Re: Job Skills Education Program (JSEP) and Cast-Off Youth, 1988 January 22-February 5 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - National Service -- Papers and Speech Re: Youth Employment and Service Programs, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - National Service -- "Towards a System of Youth Development" (testimony before U.S. Congress Hearing on Youth Employment by Gordon Berlin), 1984 March 26 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - National Service -- Correspondence Re: Feedback for National Service Study Plan by Richard Danzig and Peter Szanton, Summary of Plan, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - National Service -- National Service Task Force -- Memoranda, Grant Recommendations, Reports, Background, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - National Service -- National Service Task Force -- Memoranda, 1985 May 27-1986 February 24 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - National Service -- Memoranda Re: Notes and Materials for College Presidents' Meeting, 1986 January 7 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - National Service -- Correspondence Re: City Volunteer Corps and Vista, 1986 August 11-1987 April 8 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - National Service -- Workshop on School-Sanctioned Community Service -- Memoranda, Agenda, 1986 October 10-1987 March 18 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - National Service -- Correspondence and Statements Supporting National Service Legislation, 1986 November 6-1987 June 18 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - National Service -- Gordon Berlin Notes on National Service, 1987 May 18 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - New York City Welfare Policy and HRA Task Force -- HRA Employment Issues Meeting -- Agenda, Participants List, Notes, Background, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - New York City Welfare Policy and HRA Task Force -- New York City Welfare Reform Study Group Meeting -- Correspondence, Draft Option Papers, Agenda, Notes, 1987 February-May (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - New York City Welfare Policy and HRA Task Force -- Correspondence Re: HRA Opportunities for Independence (OFI) Plan, 1987 April-1988 May (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Preschool Education and Child Care -- Papers on Maternity Care and Early Childhood Education for At-Risk Youth, 1987 October 20-December 3 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Preschool Education and Daycare -- Memoranda, Meeting Summaries, Notes, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Preschool Education and Daycare -- Early Childhood Care Staff Training -- Correspondence, Proposal, Notes, 1984 October 26-1985 March 21 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Preschool Education and Daycare -- Papers, Articles, Conference Book, 1984 December 10-1986 September 12 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Preschool Education and Daycare -- Center for Successful Child Development Renewal Proposal for FY 1987-1988, Notes, 1987 June 1-22 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Poverty and Welfare -- Work Incentive Program (WIN) -- Memoranda, Research Plan, Notes, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Poverty and Welfare -- Papers on Government Labor and Employment Policy, 1983 April-1985 August (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Poverty and Welfare -- Draft Papers on Welfare Policy, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Poverty and Welfare -- Public Housing -- Correspondence, Proposal, Reports, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Poverty and Welfare -- Research on "Underclass", 1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Poverty Research -- Gordon Berlin Notes, circa 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Poverty Research -- Transcripts of Executive Panel Session on Poverty (1 of 2), 1986 September 11-12 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Poverty Research -- Transcripts of Executive Panel Session on Poverty (2 of 2), 1986 September 11-12 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Poverty Research -- National Puerto Rican Coalition Meeting on Puerto Rican Poverty -- Correspondence, Background, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Project on Social Welfare Policy and the American Future, 1985 February 1-1987 December 4 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - School Drop-Out in At-Risk Youth -- Oregon Youth Coordinating Council Report to the Governor, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - School Drop-Out in At-Risk Youth -- Memoranda, Notes, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - School-to-Work Transition -- Gary Walker Correspondence Re: Youth Trainee Businesses, 1984 February 10 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - School-to-Work Transition -- "From School to Work: Transition or Chasm?" (Gordon Berlin paper and notes), 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Seedco - Memoranda, Notes, Background, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Site Visits to Urban Poverty Programs for Youth Work, Service and Learning, 1986 January 30 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Summer Youth Employment Program -- Gordon Berlin Notes, circa 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Summer Youth Employment Program -- Correspondence, Notes, Program Information, 1983 July 15-1985 April 4 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Summer Youth Employment Program -- Budget Summary, Funding, Cost Reduction Plan, 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Summer Youth Employment Program -- Correspondence, Proposed Federal Employment Programs, 1986 February 5-May 30 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Robert A. Taggart Working File -- MacArthur Fellowship Support, Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports on the Remediation and Training Institute (1 of 2), 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Robert A. Taggart Working File (2 of 2), 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Task Force on Growth, Development and Employment -- Proposals, Reports, Memoranda, Agenda, 1984 March 30-1987 October 23 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Teen Pregnancy -- Bibliography, Statistical Charts, 1984 September-1985 May (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Urban Poverty Program Review, 1985 September 4-1988 May 17 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Women's Self-Employment -- Memoranda, Background, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Women and Poverty -- Memorandum and Report on Teenage Pregnancy and Reproductive Health, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Workfare/Welfare Reform -- "Work Requirement Programs in the 1980s: The Welfare Example" (report), 1981 June (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Workfare/Welfare Reform -- Correspondence, Notes, 1982-1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Workfare/Welfare Reform -- Gordon Berlin Statement on Workfare Programs, 1982 March 26 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Workfare/Welfare Reform -- Summary of Legislation and Policy Issues, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Workfare/Welfare Reform -- Correspondence Re: Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation Meeting on Welfare Reform, 1987 June 23 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Work Force 2000 Meetings -- Agenda, Memoranda, Discussion and Background Papers, Clippings, Mar 28, 1986-Jan 20, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Youth Service Programs -- New York City Volunteer Corps -- Memoranda, Program Information, Statistical Summary, Jun 30, 1986-Jan 21, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Youth Unemployment -- Notes, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Speeches and Writings, 1983-1985; III
  This series of three files contains Mr. Berlin's statement to a joint Congressional and Senate Field Hearing on the subject of youth employment (1983), a draft article titled "Employment and Income Generation, Plant Closings and Worker Ownership" with editorial comments by Susan Berresford (1984), and a speech titled "The Foundation's Youth Work, Service and Learning Strategy: A Site Visit Overview" given to the Trustees before a tour of three youth programs (1985).
  - Gordon Berlin Statement before Northeast-Midwest Congressional and Senate Coalition's Field Hearing on Institutional Roles in Youth Employment, Jun 1983 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - "Employment and Income Generation, Plant Closings and Worker Ownership: The Case for a Foundation" (draft article with comments by Susan Berresford), Aug 7, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - "The Foundation's Youth Work, Service and Learning Strategy: A Site Visit Overview", speech given to the Board of Trustees, Jun 26, 1985, Jun 26-Jul 18, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Subject and Correspondence Files, 1982-1987; IV
  This series contains correspondence files and subject files. Topics of subject files include the appointment of consultants (1982) and affirmative action (1985).
  The corespondence files are arranged chronologically. The subject files are arranged alphabetically.
  - Appointment of Consultants Policy Memoranda, Feb 1, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Chron File -- Site Visit Reports, Policy-Relevant Correspondence and Memoranda, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Employee Ownership, Jun 15-Jul 17, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Chron File -- Business and Employment Memoranda, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Chron File -- Trustee Visit Memoranda, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Industrial Competitiveness, Jan 21, 1985-Nov 6, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Affirmative Action -- Ford Foundation Minority Pipeline Task Force, Jul 3, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Budget Memoranda, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Chron File -- Urban Poverty Programs, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Re: Feedback on Papers, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Staff Interest in Outside Organizations, Permission to Serve on Urban Institute Advisory Panel, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Beethoven Project -- Evaluation of Project, Jun 24, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Towards A More Perfect Union -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Distribution of Book, Aug 4, 1987-Apr 21, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Community Development Credit Program -- Memoranda, Report, Nov 20, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 14)